== srt字幕转制 ==
一八一七年九月
巴黎年轻有为的诗人保罗魏尔伦
收到一封署名为蓝波
寄来的八首奇特的诗篇
作者署名：蓝波
他立即回信道：
“亲爱的伟大灵魂
来我们这儿吧，期待你”
以下故事
直接源自他们的书信和诗篇
魏尔伦是大诗人之时
蓝波是个革命性的天才
他16岁到19岁的作品
永远改变了现代诗的面貌
主演：莱昂纳多.迪卡普里奥
主演：戴维.休利斯
主演：罗曼娜.波林热
导演：阿涅斯卡.霍兰
有时他用多愁善感的语调
Sometimes he speaks in a kind of tender dialect
述说引人悔恨的死亡
of the death which causes repentance...
述说活着的忧伤人群
of the unhappy men who certainly exist...
述说悲伤世事，生死离别
of painful tasks and heartrending departures.
In the hovels where we got drunk...
在我们喝得酩酊大醉的简陋小屋
他泪眼观望围绕在身旁的
he wept looking at those who surrounded us...
a cattle of poverty.
那些没用的贫苦的人
他在乱街扶起醉鬼
He lifted up drunks in the black streets.
他同情惨遭恶母虐待的孩子
He had the pity a bad mother has for small children.
他的动作如教义课上的女孩那般优雅
He moved with the graceof a little girl at catechism.
他假装通晓一切
He pretended to know about everything...
商业、艺术、医学
business, art, medicine.
我追随他
I followed him.
我必须如此
I had to.
先生，有人找你，在那边
Someone for you, sir. Over there.
我认识她吗？
Do I know her?
她有名片给我
She gave me her card.
伊莎蓓·兰波
Isabella Rimbaud.
请…
Please...
请坐
Please sit down.
安迪一直在照顾你吧？
Has Andre been looking after you?
喝点什么吗？
Can I get you something to drink?
不用，谢谢
No, thank you.
请坐
Please.
这真的是只是公事公办
It's really a business matter...
我想和你谈谈
I want to discuss with you, Mr. Verlaine.
这是几个月前出版的
This was published a few months ago...
完全未经授权的家兄的诗集
a completely unauthorized selection of my brother's poems.
家母和我想杜绝这类事情再发生
My mother and I are anxious to prevent anything like this from happening again.
我们想也许你可以帮忙
We thought you might be able to help us.
I? How?
我？怎么帮？
我知道你存有家兄的很多手稿
I understand you have a large number of my brother's manuscripts.
我是有一些，没错
I have some, yes.
如蒙归还
Well, my mother and I would be very grateful...
家母与我不胜感激
if you would return them.
我总是……极其谨慎地
I've always tried to use the utmost discretion...
处理关于令兄的事
in everything concerning your brother.
可以说我一直都在维护他的利益
I think I can say I've always defended his interests.
说来也怪
Sometimes I wonder why, since in many ways...
因为那在很多方面都跟我的利益相冲突
they're diametrically opposed to my own.
我不明白
I don't see how.
许多年后世人才理解令兄的作品
It took many years for your brother's work to be understood...
一旦他成名
but once his name began to be known...
我们的那一套便气数殆尽
it soon became clear that our ways were numbered.
单凭旧体诗的音乐性已远远不够
The music of old-fashioned verse was no longer enough.
他把我们扫地出门
He swept us away.
我并不介意，你明白么？
Not that I mind, you understand.
我知道我也曾经是个好作家
I know I was once a good writer.
我不知道他这么出名
I didn't know his name was so well-known.
如今年轻一代了解他
Yes. The young understand him now.
他是未来之声
He's the voice of the future.
对我来说最重要的
What matters to me most...
是我们合创最佳作品
is that we did our best work together.
我们两人
Both of us.
巴黎，1871年
早上好
Morning!
我来找保罗魏尔伦
I'm looking for Paul Verlaine.
你是兰波先生吗？
Are you Monsieur Rimbaud?
是
Yes.
魏尔伦没跟你一起回来？
Monsieur Verlaine is not with you, then?
没有
No.
他去车站接你
He went to the station to meet you.
他不知道我的长相
He doesn't know what I look like, does he?
我是傅勒维夫人
I am Mrs. Maute de Fleurville...
魏尔伦的岳母
Monsieur Verlaine's mother-in-law,
这是我女儿，魏尔伦夫人
and this is my daughter...Mrs. Verlaine.
你从车站怎么来的？
How did you get from the station?
走路来的
Walked.
要梳洗一下吗？
Perhaps you'd like a wash.
不用
No.
你比我们想的还年轻
You're even younger than we imagined.
你多大了？
How old are you?
亲爱的，问人年龄不礼貌
Darling, it's not polite to ask people their ages.
我要小便
I need a piss.
若不介意，请问你多大了？
How old are you, if you don't mind my asking?
他介意
He does.
16岁
Sixteen.
你在信上写21岁
Only you did say in your letter you were twenty-one.
唔
Mm.
I noticed you at the station...
在火车站的时候我注意到你
不过我没想到那就是你
彼此彼此
Likewise.
你寄给我的那些诗
Those poems you sent me...
以21岁而言，真了不起
were remarkable for someone of twenty-one.
对于一个16岁的人来说 更是史无前例
For someone of sixteen , they're unprecedented.
所以我才自称21岁
That's why I told you I was twenty-one.
我不想让你还没读诗就先觉得屈尊了
I didn't want you to feel patronizing before you'd read them.
当然
Of course.
但愿令堂没有太生我的气
I hope your mother isn't too angry with me.
没有
No.
当她知道是你出旅费的时候看起来挺高兴
Once she'd found out you'd sent the fare she seemed quite happy.
Monsieur Rimbaud? Charleville?
你是来自亚耳宁么，蓝波先生？查理维镇？
You... You come from the Ardennes, don't you,
对
Yes.
是个怡人的小镇吧？
Pleasant town, Charleville, isn't it?
最烂的地方
Last place on God's earth.
令尊是做什么的？
and what does your father do?
想必是在喝酒
Drinks mostly, I believe.
我们十年没见过他了
We haven't seen him for ten years.
对不起
I'm sorry.
不必，走了对他也好
No need to be. He's very well out of it.
晚餐后请你朗诗
Perhaps you'd like to read something to us after dinner.
不行
No. I don't think so.
- Why not?    - I Don't want to.
- 为什么？
- 我不想
我从不朗读我的诗
I never read out my poetry.
别的诗人都朗读他们的诗
All the other poets do.
别人怎么样我没兴趣
I'm not interested in what all the other poets do.
我们有聚会
We have soirees.
你不认为诗人可以互相学习么？
Don't you think poets can learn from one another?
只有那些烂诗人才会
Only if they're bad poets.
你知道这是什么么？
You know about this?
我知道是什么
I know what it is.
这是诗人的第三只眼
It's the poet's third eye.
它能融化冰河
Melts glasses.
你认为我太太如何？
What do you think of my wife?
我不知道
I don't know.
你认为呢？
What do you think of her?
她还是只是个孩子
She's still only a child, of course.
我也是啊
So am I.
苦艾酒，两杯
Absinthe, two.
你应该为出书做准备
You should do something about getting it published.
为什么？
Why?
为什么？作家都要出书
Why? Because that's what writers do.
我毫不在乎出书
I couldn't care less about being published.
最重要的是写作本身
The only thing that matters is the writing itself.
其余都是文学
Everything else is literature.
- Your last book...   - Yes?
- 你最新一本书
- 怎么了？
不够好
wasn't good enough.
你认为不好？
You don't think so?
婚前的垃圾
Premarital garbage.
不对，是情诗
No. Love poems.
很多人觉得很美
A lot of people found them very beautiful.
满纸的谎言
But they're all lies.
不是谎言，我爱她
They're not lies. I love her.
- 爱？  - 对
- Love?  - Yes.
- No such thing.    - What do you mean?
- 没那回事     - 什么意思?
将家人和夫妻连在一起的
Whatever it is binds families and married couples together...
并不是爱
that's not love.
是愚笨、 自私或恐惧
That's stupidity or selfishness or fear.
爱不存在
Love doesn't exist.
你错了
You're wrong.
那是利己主义
Self-interest exists.
植根于自身利益的依恋
Attachment based on personal gain exists.
或是自我满足
Complacency exists.
但爱不存在
But not love.
爱必须重新创造
Love has to be reinvented.
他为何这么想逃避现实？
Why did he want so much to escape from reality?
从未有人抱持这种目标
There never was a man with such an aim.
也许他知道改变生命的秘密？
Did he perhaps know secrets to change life?
"有时我见到了
"Sometimes I've seen...
人们自以为所见的"
"what people think they've seen."
他跟我想像的不同
He's not how I imagined him.
“我流太多的泪
"I've wept too many tears...
心碎的黎明”
"heartbreaking dawns."
我比较喜欢你的诗
I prefer your poems.
我不大看得懂那种东西
I don't really understand that kind of thing.
不
No.
不，这是新诗
No. This is something new.
“我已流太多泪”
"I've wept too many tears...
“心碎的黎明”
"heartbreaking dawns."
怎么了？
What is it?
他在踢
He's kicking.
你看？
You see?
这里，及这里
There, there
你不觉得让他在你的朋友那住些日子会更好一些吗
Don't you think it would be more sensible to get one of your friends to put him up for a while?
别人都不理解他
People don't understand him.
只有我能
I'm the only one who understands him.
父亲显然不会理解他
Well, Daddy certainly won't understand him.
看来你还没意识到，今年我支持这场革命
You don't seem to realise, we had a revolution this year which I supported.
我可能会丧命
I could have been shot.
如果我没有丢了工作
If I hadn't been thrown out of my job...
就算是只有一秒钟，难道你以为我会接受你父亲他妈的施舍么？
you think I would have accepted your father's damn charity?
我不过是帮助一位朋友
For God's sake, all I'm doing is helping a friend!
为什么我们一定要遭受这种待遇？我可是你丈夫！
Why do we go through all this? I'm your husband!
对不起，保罗
I'm sorry, Paul.
你是想惹我发火？
Are you trying to annoy me?
我没有
No.
那就别
Well, don't.
晚安，大家都睡了
Evening! Everyone's in bed, I'm afraid...
还是你是来找那个老家伙的？
unless you've come to see the old boy.
The old boy?
那个老家伙？
就是莫德傅勒维，你不是他的朋友吧？
Maute de Fleurville, Not a friend of his, are you?
不是
No.
有没有兴趣买个十字架？
You wouldn't like to buy a crucifix, would you?
我会以最合理的价钱卖给你
I can let you have this one on extremely reasonable terms.
我看是真珍珠做的
It's made with real pearls, I think.
你他妈的到底是谁？
Who the hell are you?
我也想问你这个问题
I might ask you the same question...
如果不是我够礼貌的话
Except I'd be more polite.
我就是莫德傅勒维
I am Maute de Fleurville.
啊
Ah.
这是我打碎了的你的狗狗
Then this is your dog I just broke.
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
狗都是自由主义者
Dogs are all liberals.
什么时候你能不经我的允许
Since when have you had the right...
就请人住到家里了？
to invite people to stay in this house without my permission?
如果我连在自己家里招待客人的权利都没有
If I can't put up a guest in my own home...
那我宁愿住到别处去
when I feel like it, I might as well live somewhere else.
如果你不是成天游游荡荡 你就可以租得起房子
If you weren't so idle, you might be able to afford to.
- 你很清楚自从社区    - 别找藉口
- You know very well since the Commune...  - Any excuse.
你也不见得就多努力工作
I don't notice you working your fingers to the bone.
你再碰到那个小混混时
When you next see that hooligan...
请他归还他偷走的东西
you'll kindly ask him to return the objects he's pilfered.
- 你在说什么？  - 他会明白我的意思的
- What are you talking about?  - He'll know what I mean.
那你就自己去说
Then ask him yourself.
我很乐意告诉你，他已经走了
I'm happy to say, he's left the house.
What?
什么？
谢天谢地
Thank God.
我以为再也找不到你
I thought I was never going to find you.
我不知道那老家伙捣什么鬼
I don't know what that bastard thought he was doing.
- 那是他的家    - 是的
- It's his house.    - Yes.
走
Come.
我给你找个地方
We'll find you somewhere.
来呀
Come on
恐怕只有这样了
It's not much, I'm afraid.
- Just for a few days.    - It's fine.
- 反正就待几天    - 这儿很好
你爱她吗？
So do you love her?
当然，她十全十美
Of course. She's ideal.
18岁，漂亮、有钱
Eighteen, beautiful, plenty of money...
贤惠，怀上了我的孩子
all the wifely virtues. And she's about to give me a baby.
你们有共同点吗？
Do you have anything in common?
没有
No.
她聪明吗？
Is she intelligent?
不
No.
她能理解你吗？
Does she understand you?
不能
No.
那她唯一能带给你的就是性
Then the only thing she can give you is sex.
保罗，保罗
Paul , Paul
Hi!
嗨！
Hey!
嘿！
找到他了吗？
Did you find him?
找到了
I did.
那他还给你父亲的十字架了吗？
And did he give you back Daddy's crucifix?
如果你父亲能赶走一个一贫如洗的孩子
If your father's capable of throwing that boy out without a peny...
他就不配把十字架挂在墙上
he's got no right having Christ hanging all over his walls.
你们这些人根本就不知道什么是贫穷
You people don't understand what poverty is.
你知道在查理维镇，如果他想看一本书
Do you realise that in Charleville, if he wanted a book...
还得去偷
he had go and steal it.
那恰恰证明了他的为人
That proves what kind of person he is.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你不该那样说他的
You shouldn't have said that.
对不起
I'm sorry.
- 怎么了？  - 没什么
- What's going on?   - Nothing.
亲爱的，你没事吧？
Are you all right, my dear?
我没事
Yes, I'm all right.
去年夏天战时
It was last summer during the war...
我离家出走的一回
one of the many times I ran away from home.
我到河边装水
I came down to the river to fill my water bottle...
有个没比我大多少的普鲁士兵
and there was a Prussian soldier, not much older than me...
在空地上睡觉
asleep in the clearing.
我看了许久才明白
I watched him for a long time before I realised...
他不是睡着
he wasn't asleep.
他是死了
he was dead.
这使我想通了
And somehow that clarified things for me.
我若想成为本世纪第一诗人
I understood that what I needed...
我需要做的
to become the first poet of this century...
就是用我的身体力行一切
was to experience everything in my body.
作为一个人已不够
It was no longer enough for me to be one person.
我决定要成为每个人
I decided to be everyone.
I decided to be a genius.
我决定要成为一名天才式的人物
我决定要开创未来
I decided to originate the future.
谢谢
Thank you.
它的原理和摄影很相似
The principle is very like photography...
只不过不是拍下人的相貌
only instead of photographing a man's face...
而是记下他的声音
you photograph his voice.
二十年后
Then twenty years later...
就像打开相簿
just as you'd open a photograph album...
你只要将柱体放入机器
you simply put the relevant cylinder into the paleophone...
就能听见诗人读他的诗
and you listen to a poet reading his... reading his poems...
或唱歌
or singing his songs.
你认为你能发明
And you think you... you could invent...
那么一种机器么?
a machine like that which worked?
天, 我们走吧
For Christ's sake, let's get the fuck out of here.
- 不行    - 为什么？
- We can't.   - Why not?
- 他快要开始了   - 哪个？
- He's about to start reading.   - Which one is it?
艾卡，那儿那个
Aicard.  Over there.
我不会喜欢他的
Oh, I don't think I'm going to like him very much.
魏尔伦给我看过你的诗
Verlaine showed me some of your poems.
Oh, Yes?
噢，是吗？
了不起，很有前途
Remarkable. Very promising.
只是，好像巧妙的构思被污染了..
Only it seems to me all that ingenuity is rather marred by...
好像一个青年急切的想引起注意...
Well, not exactly a juvenile urge to shock...
类似这种意思
but something of the sort.
- 引起你注意了？   - 没
- And were you shocked?  - No, I wasn't of course not.
那为什么你要假设我打算让你注意？
Then why would you suppose I intended you to be?
问题不在这里
That's not really the point.
我觉得理所当然
Seems fair enough to me.
我反对你用的技巧
I could object to your technical approach.
我反对你的领结
I could object to your tie.
他不喜欢讨论他的诗
He doesn't like discussing his poetry.
I see.
我懂了
给我们的朋友一个惊喜
I have a surprise for our friend.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢各位
Thanke you, thank you, gentlemen.
- Sulfuric acid    - My first poem is written expressly for children.
- 硫酸       - 第一首是童诗
请各位记住
I would ask you to bear this in mind...
所有有价值的儿童文学，
although, as with all worthwhile work for children...
其实都不是完全和成年人无关的
it's hoped what is said is of some relevance to adults.
这首诗名为“绿色苦艾酒”
The poem is called "Green Absinthe."
绿色苦艾酒是受诅咒者的药
Green absinthe is the potion of the damned...
阻塞血管的致命毒药
a deadly poison silting up the veins...
妻儿在贫贱中哭泣时
while wife and child sit weeping in their slum...
- 我不信   - 醉汉将苦艾酒倾入脑中
- I don't believe it.   - A drunkard pours absinthe into his brains.
- Shit.   - Oh drunkard, most contemptible of men...
- 狗屁     - 酒鬼呀，最可厌的男人
- Shit!     - Be quiet.
- 放屁       - 安静
退化、堕落、罪恶、愚钝
Degarded, fallen, sinful, and obtuse...
- 完全狗屁不通！  - 别说了
- It is! It's authentic shit!   - Please!
退化、堕落、罪恶、愚钝
...degraded, fallen, sinful, and obtuse...
我喜欢
I like it!
你无所顾忌殴打妻儿
You scruple not to beat your wife and child...
因为不给你酒喝
For trying to deprive you of the juice!
- Get out, you !   - Me?
- 你滚出去    - 我吗？
对，就是你，你这个惹人厌的小杂种  快滚，不然就给你扔出去
Yes, you, you offensive little bastard. Get out, or I'll throw you out.
我想应该允许我提出异议
Oh, I think I may, may I not, be permitted to raise some objection...
法国诗被如此瞎搞
against the butchering of French poetry?
你没有这个权利，道完歉就滚
No, you may not. Now apologize and get out!
别再靠近我
Don't come any nearer.
小心
Be careful!
你以为你能吓着我
You think you can frighten me with that thing...
小心呀！
Careful! Careful, I say!
Careful!
小心！
出去！
Get out!
来呀
Come here.
你他妈的尿墨水的！现在到你了！
Now you, you fucking inkpisser!
Come here!
过来！
在弗郎沙时代
In the days of Francois Premier...
善良睿智的伟人们在乡间漫步
wise and benevolent giants roamed the countryside...
他们的主要职务之一
And one of their primary functions...
就是清除世界上的学究
was to rid the world of pedants...
蠢材和和毫无才华的作家
fools and writers of no talent...
而方法就是从高处往他们身上撒尿！
by pissing on them from a great height.
这就是怎么在文学界立足
How to make your way in the literary world.
这个城市让人失望的就是…
The depressing thing about this city...
搞艺术的比中产阶级还他妈的要中产阶级
is that the artists are even more bourgeois than the fucking bourgeoisie.
我们作个协定
We should make a bargain.
你帮助我，我就帮助你
You help me, and I'll help you.
如果你随我一起出走
If we go away together...
我保证你们一定能再创佳作
I'm sure you'll be able to start doing good work again.
各自取长补短之后
And when we've taken as much as we can from each other...
我们再分道扬镳
we simply split up and move on.
我们怎样度日？
And how would we live?
你有钱的吧？
You have some money, don't you?
我懂了
I understand.
我资助你
I help you by supporting you...
你帮我擦亮生命的灵感
and you help me by renewing my rusty old inspiration.
Is that it?
是这意思吧？
也不尽然
Not altogether.
Where have you been?
你去哪儿了？
我想我大概碍事了
I thought I'd probably just get in the way.
Don't shout.
别嚷！
会吵到孩子
You'll wake the baby.
Is it a boy?
是男孩？
对
Yes.
怪模怪样的小家伙
Funny-looking little bugger.
不要
Don't.
好吧
All right.
谢谢你
Thank you.
真感谢你
No.
不要
拜托，不要
Please...no
Why not?
为什么不？
The baby was born.
小孩都生下来了
不要
No.
- Isabelle!    - I didn't know you were coming.
- 伊莎贝拉！  - 我不知道你要回来
那个黑暗之嘴在哪？
Where is the mouth of darkness?
妈妈？她跟维达莉在田里
Mother? She's in the fields with Vitalie.
你想见她吗？
Do you want to see her?
No.
不想
谢谢
Thanks.
Are you back for good?
你回来就永远不走了么？
永远我不知道
For good? I don't know.
For better or worse.
再说吧
田里有事要做
Because there's work to be done in the fields.
我这里也有事要做
There's work to be done here.
我以为你在巴黎混出名堂了
I thought you were getting on well in Paris.
本来就是，但最近魏尔伦的老婆开始找麻烦
I was. But Verlaine's wife started to make trouble.
什么麻烦？
What kind of trouble?
她扬言要离婚
Threatening a divorce, you know...
她认为我跟维尔伦呆在一起的时间太长
she thought we were spending too much time together.
娇生惯养的富家女，是吧？
Spoiled rich girl, I suppose.
没错
That's right.
你在做的事…
This work you're doing...
有前途么？
is it the kind of thing that will lead to anything?
我不知道
I don't know.
但这是我要做的事
Nevertheless, it's the kind of work I do.
我想巴黎没这么刺激吧
I don't suppose Paris ever gets as exciting as this.
你看起来就像他妈的圣女
You look like a fucking saint.
就差个光环了
Except you haven't got your halo.
我来给你个光环
I'll give you your halo.
他回来了，是吗？
He's back, isn't he?
我现在不能离开她
I can't leave Mathilde at the moment.
她身体不好
She's not very well.
I'm not surprised if you keep setting fire to her.
这到不奇怪，谁让你老是放火烧她。
星期四后我就没再烧过她
I haven't set fire to her since Thursday.
No, it's not very funny.
这不怎么好笑
不是可笑，是可悲
No, it's pathetic.
你的怪异暴行不是一般地让人恶心
Your acts of violence are always curiously disgusting.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
一点都不干脆
They're not clean.
你老是醉得恍恍惚惚的
You're always in some sort of a drunken stupor.
事后就开始道歉乞怜
Then you start apologizing and groveling.
我不喜欢伤害人
I don't like hurting people.
那就别做
Then don't.
你要是做，就痛快点
But if you do, do it coolly.
别用道歉来侮辱受害者
Don't insult your victims by feeling sorry afterwards.
我爱她，你是知道的
I love her, you see.
不可能
You can't possibly.
我爱她的肉体
I love her body.
- There are other bodies.    - No.
- 肉体有的是     - 不
不
No.
我爱玛蒂德的肉体
I love Mathilde's body.
不爱她的灵魂？
But not her soul?
我认为爱肉体比爱灵魂更重要
I think it's less important to love the soul than to love the body.
毕竟灵魂可能是永存的
After all, the soul may be immortal.
我们有的是时间去爱
We have plenty of time for the soul...
但肉体会腐烂
but flesh rots.
正是我对肉体的爱使我保持了忠诚
It's my love of flesh which keeps me faithful.
Faithful？
忠诚？
什么意思？
What do you mean?
我忠于所有的爱人
I'm faithful to all my lovers...
因为只要我曾经爱过他们
because once I love them,
我就会永远爱他们
I will always love them.
不管我是在夜间
And when I'm alone in the evening...
或是在茫茫清晨时独处
or in the early morning
我会闭上眼睛
I close my eyes
赞颂他们每一个人
and I celebrate them all.
那不是忠贞，是怀旧
That's not faithfulness. That's nostalgia.
你要是不想离开玛蒂尔德
If you don't want to leave Mathilde,
也不是因为忠诚，而是因为你的软弱
it's not because you're faithful, it's because you're weak.
不，若强壮包括野蛮
If strength involves brutality,
我宁愿选择软弱
I prefer to be weak.
你的话，软弱也同样带着野蛮，不是么？
With you, weakness involves brutality as well. Doesn't it?
别指望我忠于你
Don't expect me to be faithful to you.
你干嘛对我这么苛刻？
Why are you so harsh with me?
因为你贱
Because you need it.
你知道
Isn't it enough for you to know...
我从没像爱你一样爱过别人
that I love you more than I've ever loved anyone
and that I'll always love you?
我会永远爱你，难道还不够吗 ？
闭嘴，你这醉鬼
Shut up, you sniveling drunk.
- 跟我说你爱我            - 哦, 天
- Tell me that you love me.     -Oh, For God's sake...
求求你
Please.
求你了  这对我很重要
Please. It's important.
Just say it.
你说呀！
你知道我很喜欢你
You know I'm very fond of you.
- Do you love me?   - What?
- 你爱我吗？
- 什么？
- Do you love me?  - Yes.
- 爱
- 你爱我吗？
那你就把手放桌上
Then put your hands on the table.
What?
什么？
把手放到桌上
Put your hand on the table.
手心朝上
Palm upwards.
唯一不能忍受的，就是没什么是不能忍受的
The only unbearable thing is that nothing is unbearable.
向前
On...
我们必须离开
We have to leave.
我不知道
I...I don't know.
时候到了
Yes. It's time.
去年离家出走的时候是我一生中最快乐的时光
The happiest days of my life was last year when I ran away from home.
没有目的地，就那么继续往前走着
I didn't know where I was going, I just carried on.
我从没有过那么快乐的日子
I've never seen such long and colored days...
只是我永远都走得不够远
and I could never get far enough.
我还从没见过海
I've never seen the sea.
我想去非洲
I wanted to walk to Africa...
穿越沙漠
and cross the desert.
我想要太阳
I wanted the sun.
I want the sun.
你明白吗？我要太阳！
Do you understand me? I want the sun!
你想去哪里？
Where do you want to go?
我不知道
I don't know.
我不管，只要离开就行
I don't care. Just away.
我现在不能离开玛蒂德
You know very well I can't leave Mathilde right now.
她身体不好
She's not very well.
那就不要
Then don't.
What?
什么？
不要离开她
Don't leave her.
Wait! Wait! Wait!
等一下
敬生命
To life.
来
Come on!
比利时，布鲁塞尔
保罗
Paul.
你还记得那些快乐的时光么？
Do you remember happier times?
你为何要离开我们？
Why did you leave us?
有风声说由于在巴黎公社期间  我在宣传部门工作过
I had a tip-off I was going to arrested for my work...
所以要遭到逮捕
in the propaganda press during the Commune.
但那是一年多以前的事了
But that was over a year ago.
警方也许效率差
Well... the police may be slow...
但总归还是行动派
but they're methodical.
我可不能忍受进监狱
I couldn't bear to go to jail.
所以我觉得最好还是在国外呆几个月
I think it's best if I stay out of the country for a few months.
与蓝波吗？
With Rimbaud?
呃
Well...
想必警方也想抓他
I suppose he's wanted by the police as well.
不
No...
你为何宁可要他？
Why do you prefer him to me?
我没
I don't.
我没有
你不用现在就穿上衣服吧？
Don't have to get dressed right away, do you?
我跟妈妈说了要一起吃早餐
I told Mummy I'd meet her for breakfast.
- What's she doing here?  - She came with me.
- 她来干什么的？
- 她陪我来的
对了，还有件事
Well, that's another thing.
我再也受不了跟你的父母一起住了
I certainly can't stand living with your parents anymore.
没有别的安全的地方了
It's not safe anywhere else.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
你明白我的意思
You know what I mean.
听我说
Listen...
我有个主意
I had this idea.
是我想出来的
I thought of this idea.
我想我们可以移民
I thought we might emigrate.
移民？去哪里？
Emigrate? Where to?
新苏格兰
New Caledonia.
你有很多公社朋友在那边
A lot of your friends from the Commune are there.
你可以写作
You'd be able to write.
就像我们刚结婚的时候，而且……
It would be like it was when we were first married and...
What?
什么？
没什么
Nothing.
不，说吧
No. Go on.
我只是想说，如果你愿意的话你可以不再……
I was only going to say that you could stop...if you wanted
我是说，如果你心甘情愿的话  那戒酒会更容易些
I mean it would be easier for you if you wanted... to stop drinking.
我把你吓坏了吧？
You're frightened of me, aren't you?
别以为我喜欢喝醉
Don't think that I like getting drunk.
我是说，我确实喜欢喝醉酒
I mean, I do like getting drunk.
但不喜欢就那么醉着
but I don't like being drunk.
不管怎样
Anyway...
我打了你之后
when I hit you...
感觉糟糕透了
I feel so terrible all I can think of...
只能借酒消愁
is to get drunk again and forget about it.
你想我们能住在茅草屋里或是其他什么地方么？
Can you see us living in a grass hut or whatever they have?
有何不可？
Why not?
Let's go, for Christ's sake, let's go. Before it's too late.
那就走吧，拜托，我们走吧。趁现在还来得及。
只要你想，我们随时都可以离开
We can go whenever you like.
现在不行
Not now!
Why not?
怎么不行？
帮我扣上这个
Help me with this.
不
No.
帮我扣这个
Help me with this.
住手
Stop!
你为何要这样对待我们？
Why are you doing this to us?
别担心
Don't worry.
他很快就会回到你身边
You can have him back quite soon...
只是有那么一点损伤
and only slightly damaged.
他已经回来了
He's coming back now.
你来做什么？
What are you doing here?
What's this?
这是什么？
“我可怜的玛蒂德
"My poor Mathilde...
别生气，别哭
"Don't be upset. Don't cry.
这是噩梦
"This is a bad dream.
有天我会醒来的  爱你的保罗”
"One day, I'll wake up. Love, Paul."
甜蜜啊，是吧？闺房和乐？
Nice, was it? A scene of conjugal bliss?
我要跟她回巴黎
I'm going back to Paris with her.
好啊
Right.
- No, wait, wait, let me explain.  - Why should I?
- 别走，等一下，听我解释
- 我干嘛要听？
不是你想象的那样，是其他事
It's not what you think. It's something else.
是她建议我们移民
She suggested we emigrate...
- 移民？     -对
- Emigrate?  -Yes.
去新苏格兰
to New Caledonia.
换个环境我就能过宁静的生活
It'd be a change for me. A quiet life.
还能戒酒   你不认为这是个好主意么？
I could stop drinking, don't you think it's a good idea?
不
No.
你根本就不在乎我是不是快乐，对吧?
You don't care about my happiness, do you?
没错，你也不该在乎
No, and neither should you.
你永远都不会明白我有多爱她
You've never been able to understand how much I love her.
今天早上我走进来，她就躺在那，光着身子躺在床上。
I walked in this morning, and she was lying there naked on the bed.
她看上去那么美，那么年轻，那么…
She looked so beautiful, so young and so...
有什么可笑的？
What's so funny?
她真的光着身子躺在床上？
Was she really lying there naked on the bed?
对啊
Yes.
那我对她的评价可就要大幅度提高了
Then my estimation for her goes up a long way.
什么意思？为什么？
What do you mean? Why?
因为她了解你想要什么并且迎合你的需要
Oh, for realizing what was needed and providing it for you.
有什么关系？她是你老婆
What does it matter? She's your wife,
你爱她，那就回她那儿去
you love her, right? Go back to her.
转车！转车！
All change! All change!
边境巡逻！
Border patrol!
请拿好你们的护照以备检查
Please have your passports ready for inspection.
边境巡逻！
Border patrol!
请拿好你们的护照以备检查
Please have your passports ready for inspection.
谢谢
Thank you.
我去买份报纸
I'm just going to find a newspaper.
别去太久
Don't be long.
玛蒂德
Mathilde
看
Look there.
- See white?   - Yeah
- 对
- 看见那白色吗？
See?
看到了吗？
那是英国
It's England.
天啊！
Oh, oh, god!
伦敦，数月后
我变成传说中的歌剧
"I became a fabulous opera.
知晓一切生物都注定快乐
"I saw that all creatures are condemned to happiness."
这是什么？ 你重拾押韵了？
What's this? Are you going back to rhyme?
"我曾研究过究竟何为快乐
"I have researched the magic shapes...
它的魔力竟令人无法逃脱"
"of the happiness no one escapes."
真是绝妙
That's wonderful.
我总是想不通为何你会选择把诗寄给我
I've often wondered why you chose to write to me.
你远远地走在前面，我甚至看不懂你的那些符号
You are so far up ahead, I can't even understand the signs you're making.
你让我觉得我不属于这个世纪
You make me feel I'm from another century.
“我曾研究过究竟何为快乐，它的魔力竟令人无法逃脱”
"I have researched the magic shapes... of the happiness no one escapes."
真妙
It's wonderful.
我会选择你当然是有原因的
I chose you for a very good reason.
是这样的
You see...
我总是知道要说什么
I've always known what to say...
而你，你却知道如何去说
but you... you know how to say.
我想我能从你那学到点什么
I thought I could learn from you...
而且我确实学到了
and I have.
你最怕什么？
What's your greatest fear?
我不想被阉
I wouldn't like to mislay my balls.
怎么了？你最怕什么？
Why, what's your greatest fear?
怕变成我眼中的别人
That other people will see me as I see them.
我们现在很缺钱
Getting quite short of money, you know.
你老说这个
So you keep saying.
该找份工作
Perhaps it's time we took a job.
我早就告诉过你了  我不打算找工作
I've told you before, I've no intention of taking a job.
我的创作太好
My work is going far too well.
不能浪费时间赚钱
I can't afford to waste time earning money.
我今早收到信
I... I had a letter this morning...
玛蒂德的律师来函
Fom Mathilde's lawyer.
And?
说什么？
她申请合法分居
She's applied for legal separation on the grounds...
因为我俩有不道德关系
that you and I are indulging in immoral relations.
And?
还有呢？
- 喜欢这帽子，先生？     - 可能吧
- Like a hat, sir?              - Possibly.
来，看看
There you are. Take a look.
他想知道咱们是否愿作医学检查
He wants to know if we're prepared to submit to a medical examination.
What?
什么？
真不知道他们到底凭什么这么非难咱们
I don't know why they think
they can make that such outrageous accusation.
等会儿……
Wait a minute...
我要回信去骂他们这帮混蛋
I'm going to write straight back,
让他们对咱们的肛门尊敬点
I'm going to say as far as I'm concerned, the whole gang of them can look up our asses.
你疯了吗？
What are you, insane?
她是被遗弃所以会获准离婚
They can give her a divorce on desertion alone.
而如果是遗弃外加鸡奸的话 我们就要坐牢了
and if it's desertion and sodomy, they can throw us both in jail.
我才不去坐牢
and I'm not going to jail.
是吗？有那么糟？
I don't know. Would it be so bad?
巴达维亚（雅加达）
Batavia...
你能听到风吹过棕榈树叶的沙沙声
You can hear the wind rustling in the palm trees.
不可能 (法语)
L'IMPOSSIBLE.
怎么了？
What's the matter?
太难了
It's so difficult.
谁想到会这么难？
Who would have imagined it would be so difficult?
我今天写信给律师了
I wrote to the lawyer today.
跟他解释说那是她父亲的错
I explained to him, it's her father who's in the wrong.
我多次要求索回我的物品
How many times have I asked for my things back from that house?
而她父亲都置之不理
And he takes no...no notice whatsoever?
是你不对
You're in the wrong.
好吧
All right.
好吧，是我不对
All right. I'm in the wrong.
是我错了，如果你想这么说的话
I'm in the wrong, if you say so.
你说是就是，对吧？
then that's established, isn't it?
我不知道
I don't know.
What... What is it?  You seem different.
这到底是怎么了？  你像变了一个人似的
没错
Yes.
是写作的缘故
It's the writing.
写作改变了我
The writing has changed me.
前进
On.
你大概认为这几周来
I suppose you think I've been just lying here...
我一直都像瘫了似的躺在床上吧？
all these weeks in a state of paralyzed sloth.
呃，倒也不是
Well, not necessarily.
我确实是
Well, I have.
但在漠然的外表下翻搅着
But bubbling beneath the surface...
并且缓缓浮现的，是崭新的体制
and rising slowly through the layers of indifference has come a new system...
树立坚韧无情
harden up
扬弃浪漫主义
reject romanticism...
抛开辞藻
abandon rhetoric...
直击要害
Get it right.
我终于见到了想征服世界的下场
And finally I've seen where my attempt to conquer the world has led me.
什么下场？
Where has it led you?
流落至此
Here.
想要体验一切却落到这步田地
My search for universal experience has led me here...
活在闲散、无意义的穷困中
to live an idle, pointless life of poverty...
被一个老诗人宠幸
as the minion of a bald, ugly...
他又秃又丑，酒气昏天的
aging, drunken lyric poet...
他死缠着我   因为他老婆不让他回去
who clings to me because his wife won't take him back.
你怎能说这种话？
How can you bring yourself to say a thing like that?
很简单
It's easy.
这是事实
It's the truth.
你就在这，就这么活着，因为你不得不如此
You're here living like this because you have to...
酗酒、做爱、自以为是的忧郁
drink and sex and a kind of complacent melancholy...
有钱就去夜夜买醉好忘记一切
and enough money to soak yourself oblivious every night.
可我不同，我在这是因为我选择了这种生活
But me... l'm here because I choose to be.
Oh, yes?
噢，是么？
当然
Yes.
And why exactly?
那到底是为什么？
为什么当初选择跟我到伦敦来？
Why did you choose to come to London with me?
显然你把这当成了你的秘密流浪的一个舞台
No doubt you regarded it as another stage in your private odyssey...
只有越陷越深
only by plunging ever deeper, if I may mix my myths...
你才有资格在诗坛往上爬
will you gain the right to graze on the slopes of Parnassus.
当然，还有简单得多的理由让你一直忍受着我
Of course there are less subtle reasons for putting up with me.
Such as?
例如呢？
例如我养着你这个事实
Such as the fact that I support you.
你的心几乎跟身体一样丑
Your mind is almost as ugly as your body.
你要去哪？
Where are you going?
- Are they fresh?   - Yes.
- 新鲜吗？
- 是的
这一只
This one.
老天，看你那一脸贱相。
God, you look such a cunt.
你去哪里？
Where are you going?
别走
Wait!
等一下，保罗
Paul, wait!
保罗
Paul.
Move!
让开！
Paul, don't go!
保罗，别走！
Come back!
回来啊！
别丢下我
Don't leave me!
Come back!
快回来呀！
对不起
I'm sorry!
真的对不起！
我怎么活下去啊？
How am I supposed to live?
回来
Come back.
求你快回来，你是我唯一的朋友
Please come back. You're my only friend.
我答应你我会乖乖的
I promise you I'll behave myself.
那只是个愚蠢的玩笑罢了
It was only a stupid joke.
先生？
Sir?
我真的好抱歉
I can't tell you how sorry I am.
When I called you, why didn't you get off the boat?
我叫你时为何不下船？
布鲁塞尔，数日后
我们一起生活了两年，难道非得这样结束么？
We lived together for two years to finish like this?
回想一下你在遇到我之前的样子
Think back to what you were before you met me.
听从你的心
Listen to your heart.
你永远的蓝波
Yours for always.
明天我就回巴黎
I'll go back to Paris tomorrow.
别
No,
听我说
look,
不会再发生这样的事了
it won't happen again,
我绝不会再丢下你一个人，我保证
I'll never walk out on you again, I promise.
对，你不会了
No, you won't.
我不会再让你有这个机会了
I'm not going to give you the chance.
- 我身无分文地呆在伦敦能干什么？   - 对不起
What was I supposed to do in London with no money?    - I'm sorry.
我当时很生气
I was very hot.
这是为什么啊？
For God's sakes, why?
我以前说过比那过分得多的话
I've said far worse things to you than that.
而且你的确是一脸贱相
You really did look like a cunt.
你去哪儿了？
Where have you been?
外面
Out.
我又去了西班牙大使馆
I went to the Spanish embassy again...
看看他们会不会改变主意    但他们没有
to see if they'd change their minds, but they wouldn't.
荒谬, 真他妈的荒谬
It's ridiculous. It's fucking ridiculous.
我说愿为他们战死
"I'm willing to fight", I said, "and die for your cause."
你们怎么能拒绝志愿者
"You can't afford to turn away volunteers."
但他们却说不要外国人
But they said they weren't taking on any foreigners.
然后我就咒他们活该战败
Then I said, "You deserve to lose the fucking war...
我希望你们战败
"and I hope you do."
你整个早上都在西班牙大使馆吗？
And were you at the Spanish Embassy all morning?
没有
No.
你喝醉了
You're drunk.
我是喝了几杯
I have, yes, had a few drinks.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
收拾行李
Packing.
你要上哪去？
Where are you going?
回洛许老家
I'm going back home to Roche.
把书写完，将它出版
I'm going to finish my book and I'm going to have it published.
噢，出版？
Oh, publish.
我以为你没把出版放在眼里呢
I thought you were far too important for that.
不管怎样，听着，我决定了，我们得回伦敦。
Anyway, listen, I've decided. We're going back to London.
我不会跟你回伦敦的
We're not going back to London.
你会的，我已经仔细考虑过了，这是目前为止最好的办法。
Yes, Yes, Yes. I've been thinking, it's by far the best idea.
那你干嘛去西班牙大使馆？
Then why did you go to the Spanish embassy?
我没去
I didn't.
别走，再考虑考虑
Don't go. Think it over.
我已经考虑过了
I've thought it over.
你知道明天是什么日子么？
Do you know what day it is tomorrow?
星期五
Friday.
是我的结婚纪念日
It's my wedding anniversary...
从上次在布鲁塞尔做爱后
and I haven't seen her, my wife...
我有一年没见过我妻子
since we made love here in Brussels nearly a year ago.
她不回我的信
She won't answer my letters.
知道么，上周我写信告诉她，三天内她不来布鲁塞尔
Do you know, I wrote her last week and told her if she didn't come to Brussels within 3 days...
我就自杀  她甚至连信都没回
I'd commit suicide. And she didn't even reply.
啊，但你也没自杀啊
Ah, but then you didn't commit suicide.
你大概觉得很可笑
I suppose you think that's funny.
不，是很可怜
No, it's pitiful.
你到底跟多少人说过要自杀？
Tell me. How many people did you write and tell you were going to committ suicide?
我真吃惊你居然没发请贴
I'm surprised you didn't send out invitations.
你怎么能这么冷酷无情？
How can you be so callous?
无情？我冷酷无情？！你把我丢在伦敦
Callous?  Callous?!  You abandon me in London...
又要我来布鲁塞尔陪你
and then summon me to Brussels and expect me to hang around...
而你却在决定到底是要离开你老婆
while you decide whether you're going to leave your wife...
参军，还是自杀？
join the army, or shoot yourself?
然后当你发现你显然一样都干不了的时候
Then when you fail to achieve any of these aims...
还要我陪你回伦敦
as you undoubtedly will, you want me to go back to London with you!
我才不去！  休想    我要离开你 ！
It's not gonna happen! Forget it. I'm leaving you!
你不能这样
You can't.
你不能！
You can't!
听我说
Look,
现在正是夏天
it's summer.
难道你不记得去年夏天我们一起出去旅行的日子...
Remember last summer when we set out...
有多么快乐?
how wonderful it was?
你记得吗？
Remember?
我们这次何不去南方看看？
Why don't we go south?
去年夏天在地中海
Late summer on the Mediterranean...
我们享受着热情
we could dedicate ourselves to warmth.
或去非洲
Or Africa.
我知道你一直想去非洲
I know you've always wanted to go to Africa.
只去一个月，快决定吧
Just for a month, then make up your mind.
去看太阳
Look at the sun.
不要
No.
为什么？
Why not?
我不能去
I can't.
没用的
It's no good.
- It's too late.   - It's not!  It's not!
- 太晚了
- 不晚！一点都不晚！
我保证还不晚
I promise you, it's not.
你若抛弃我就是杀了我
You know if you leave me, you'll kill me.
我无法……我无法忍受孤单
I can't... I can't bear to be alone.
没有别人我活不了
I don't exist without someone else.
我不管你是不是出于同情，只要留下来就行
I don't care if you stay with me out of pity, just stay!
- I can't.    - Why not?
- 我不能
- 为什么不能？
你不在乎
You don't care.
你一点都不关心我  难道你不知道这对我意味着什么么？
You have no idea what this means to me.
妈的，你别嚎了
For God's sake, stop whining!
好热
It's very hot.
脱掉外套
Take off your coat.
我会的
I will.
早上我买了点东西
I did some shopping this morning.
我买了把枪
I bought a gun.
What for?
为了什么？
为你，为我，为每个人
For you, for me, for everybody.
希望你买了很多子弹
I hope you bought plenty of ammunition.
我不会让你走的
I'm not going to let you go, you know.
这倒是个新鲜的花招，
This is a rather entertaining number.
我们还从没用过这个
We haven't seen this one before.
我要杀了你！
I'll kill you!
天，你控制一点
For God's sake, pull yourself together.
我看了你的信
I read your letter.
你求我回来的
You begged me to come back.
你说你边写边哭
You said you were crying as you wrote it.
我能看到那纸上的泪痕！
I could see your tears on the paper!
那时我还没想到典当你的衣物
That was before I thought of pawning your clothes.
我不是故意的
I didn't mean to.
瞧你干的好事
Look what you've done.
抱歉，我不是有意的
I didn't mean to. I'm sorry.
你看
Look.
噢，天，杀了我吧，开枪啊
Oh, for God's sake, kill me, shoot me.
Shoot me!
开枪呀！
我怎么开枪？你这个蠢货
How can I, you stupid fuck?
你在我手上开了个洞
You've just blown a hole in my hand.
Oh, God. What have I done?
噢，上帝，我都干了些什么？
- 你没命中   - 开门
- You missed.   -Open up.
Open up!
开门！
开门啊！
Open up in there!
你到底在布鲁塞尔干什么？
What exactly are you doing in Brussels?
我期待妻子来这儿与我会合
I was hoping my wife might come and join me here...
就像分居后她也曾经做过的那样
as she had already done on one occasion since our separation.
我不明白，一个朋友的离去
I fail to see how the departure of a friend...
竟会使你如此绝望
could have cast you into such despair.
你与兰波之间是否有……
Did there perhaps exist between you and Rimbaud...
超出友谊的关系？
other relations besides those of friendship?
没有
No.
这是我妻子和她娘家
This is a suggestion slanderously invented...
对我的诽谤
by my wife and her family.
脱下裤子，趴在桌上
Take off your trousers and lie on this, face down.
两位医生都已作证
Both doctors have testified...
根据检验
that on the basis of their examination...
他们肯定你在最近一段时间内曾有过鸡奸行为
they are satisfied that you have recently indulged in both active and passive sodomy.
Have they?
他们说的？
你否认鸡奸行为？
Do you deny you're a practicing sodomist?
正确说法应该是肛交
The word is sodomite.
不管它被称为什么
Whatever the word may be, the activity it describes...
布鲁塞尔不赞成这种行为
is not one which is encouraged in Brussels.
保罗.魏尔伦，本庭判你有罪
Paul-Marie Verlaine, the court finds you guilty...
依据刑法三九九条
under Article 399 of the penal code...
严重伤害罪，判处你……
of grievous bodily harm and sentences you...
罚金两百法郎，并监禁两年
to a fine of two hundred francs and two years' imprisonment.
又怎么了？
Now what's the matter?
魏尔伦
Verlaine.
Verlaine！
魏尔伦！
吃饭
Eat.
上帝
God.
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
我看不懂它想要说什么
I don't understand what it's supposed to mean.
我写了什么就是什么意思
It means exactly what it says...
每个字都有它的用处
word for word,
一字不多，一字不少
no more, no less.
黑森林，两年后
你好吗？
How are you?
你的念珠呢？
Where's your rosary?
我以为你戴念珠
I thought you'd have a rosary.
你在牢里真被称作耶稣？
Is it true in prison they called you Jesus Christ?
起因很突然
It happened quite suddenly.
那天我得知玛蒂德获准离婚
the day the governor told me Mathilde had been granted her divorce.
我躺下，回首一生
I lay down and looked at my life...
什么都看不到，一无所有
and saw there was nothing, nothing.
似乎我唯一能做的事就是把自己交给主
It seemed to me the only thing I could do was to submit myself to God...
请求他的宽恕
ask him to forgive me...
并帮助我面对当时的处境    而且主真的帮了我
and help me face my situation and He did.
我保证他会的
I promise you, He did.
现在你想让我们在主的庇佑下相亲相爱，对吧？
Now you want us to love each other in Jesus, am I right?
我希望你以我为榜样
I want you to follow my example.
但愿你没以为我一直在生你的气
I hope you didn't think, all this time, I might be angry with you.
我没有
No.
我知道你也没想到我会被关这么久
I know you had no idea I might be put away for so long.
我早就原谅你了
I certainly forgave you for it.
- I didn't forgive you.   - What for?
- 我没原谅你
- 为什么？
你没命中
For missing.
你为何来这里？
Tell me. Why did you come here?
我希望你找到人生的方向
I want you to find some direction in your life.
我希望主能帮你实现你的目标
I want God to help you achieve your aims.
目标？我没有目标
Aims? I have no aims.
- I mean your writing.    - I've stopped writing.
- 我是指你的写作
- 我封笔了
我不懂……
I don't understand...
那就换个说法
Let me put it another way.
我不再写作了
I no longer write.
为什么？
Why not?
因为我已经没什么好说的了
Because I have nothing more to say.
其实一开始就没什么可说的
If I ever had anything to say in the first place.
胡扯
Nonsense.
我曾以为我能做些什么，你知道
I thought that what I did would make a difference, you know,
改变世界
change the world.
我想一切都将不同
I thought nothing would ever be the same again.
但都没用
But it's no good.
世界太老，没新鲜事
The world is too old, there's nothing new,
话都已经被别人说过了
it's all been said.
但由你来说就不同.你有天赋
Not in the way you can say it. You have a gift.
别为不实际的期望而放弃
It's no good throwing it away because your expectations were unrealistic.
你应该改变的是期望
It's the expectations you should change.
天赋是我的，我想怎样就怎样
It's my gift, I can do what I like with it.
你不能放弃，你甚至还没开始呢
You can't give up, you've hardly begun.
别担心  我会很好的
Don't worry. I'll be very good at it.
没人能动得了我：
No one will be able to touch me:
沉默的天才
The master of silence.
如果我们不说，谁来阐述真理？
But if we don't, who's going to tell the truth?
三年前，你说真理是这个，真理是那个
Three years ago, you said the truth was this and the truth was that.
然后天使降临
Then along comes the angel of the Lord...
你的真实随即改观
and the next day the truth is something completely different.
但我已经改变了，变了
But I've changed, change...
我想这正是你想要的
I thought that was what you wanted.
变了，你么？
You've changed, have you?
Yes!
是的！
那就在这，在这片荒野中
Then here, in the wilderness...
我让你做个选择：
I offer you an archetypal choice:
是要我的身体，
a choice between my body,
还是我的灵魂
and my soul.
选吧
Choose.
选啊
你的身体
Your body.
看，你的主的九十八道伤口爆裂，鲜血直流
Let the ninety-eight wounds of Our Savior burst and bleed.
别
Don't.
听我说，我曾坐在牢房里
Listen... I sat in my cell...
想着我们能有多快乐
and thought how happy we could be.
这应该很容易的，这该是世上最容易的事
It should be, should be the easiest thing in the world.
为何没能实现呢？
Why isn't it?
因为我们根本办不到
Because it never worked for us.
我们俩谁也办不到
and it will never work for either of us.
我曾想咱们两个人能一起离开
I wanted us to go away together.
嗯
Yes.
我该做些什么？
What am I going to do?
你得另找别人
You'll have to find somebody else.
我做不到，求你了
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, I can't, please.
放手
Let go.
求求你
Please.
Let go! Let go!
放开！放手！
我会带着钢铁般的四肢归来
"I shall return with limbs of steel...
还有黝黑的皮肤和愤怒的双眼
"a dark skin and a wrathful eye.
我将富有：
"I shall have money:
变得残酷无情，无所事事
"I shall be cruel and idle.
我将得到救赎
"I'll be saved."
What?
这是什么？
他的诗
Something he wrote.
我的意思是，维尔伦先生，坦白地说
The point is, Mr. Verlaine, to speak frankly...
他年轻时候写了很多诗作
a number of the poems he wrote in extreme youth...
是非常淫秽
were quite indecent...
甚至亵渎神灵的
and in some cases, even profane.
他绝不想因为这些而被世人记住
He would never have wished to be remembered for them.
是的，家母和我计划去芜存菁
My mother and I plan to destroy those of his works
销毁那些不好的作品
we feel he would have destroyed himself
我明白了
I see.
或许你还不知道
What you may not know...
亚瑟皈依天主教了
is that Arthur was converted.
皈依了？
Converted?
我对他讲道理
I reasoned with him...
他病时我为他祈祷数周
and prayed for him for weeks while he was ill...
最终他要求忏悔
and eventually he asked to be confessed.
上帝给了他足够的时间忏悔
God kept him alive long enough to repent...
他会得到救赎的
so that he could be saved.
他出了什么事？
What was the matter with him?
他的膝盖长了肿瘤
He had a tumor on his knee.
真是怪事
That's very strange.
Why?
怎么？
因为我正好也有这毛病：膝盖上长了肿瘤
That's what I have: a tumor on my knee.
他在阿比西尼亚待了十年
He spent ten years in Abyssinia.
他的足迹遍布整个国家
He explored the whole country...
深入白人从未去过的地方
places no white man had ever been...
他在哈勒尔经营贸易站
and he ran a trading post in Harar.
那地方没有医生
There was no doctor there...
但他不愿放下工作
but he wouldn't leave his work.
他坚持到疼得再也无法忍受
He insisted on staying until the pain became unbearable.
然后自己设计一具担架
Then he designed himself a litter...
雇了十人抬到海边
and hired ten men to carry him to the coast.
航程超过两星期
The journey took more than two weeks.
在非洲时…
In Africa...
他会写诗吗？
Did he write poetry?
没有
No.
On!
向前！
一抵达法国
First, as soon as he arrived...
他就进了马塞的医院
he went into the hospital in Marseilles...
他们锯掉了他的腿
and they cut off his leg.
怎么了？
What's the matter?
你看见那些从天而降的马车了么？
Can you see the carriages driving in the sky?
我必须要帮助别人，你知道
I have to help people, you see.
这是我的责任
It's my duty.
我知道
I know you do.
我不想要钱，除非它们浸透了鲜血
I don't want money, unless it's drenched in blood.
嗯
Ssh.
或许海水能冲洗掉污痕
Maybe the sea will wash away the stains.
也许
Maybe.
有件事，伊莎贝拉，你一定要答应我
There's one thing, Isabelle, you must promise me,
这很重要，你能答应我么？
it's very important, will you promise?
什么事？
What?
绝不要让他们截肢
Never let them amputate.
他只肯在家停留一个月
He would only stay at home a month.
他一直说，他得返回太阳下
He kept saying he had to travel back towards the sun,
太阳能治愈他
that the sun would heal him.
请别站起来了
Please, don't get up.
我送你回旅馆
Let me see you to your hotel.
不用了，很荣幸……
No, no. It was an honor...
见到您这样一位杰出的诗人
to meet such a distinguished poet.
能见到您这样的夫人是我的荣幸
A pleasure to meet you.
你有我的名片吗？
You have my card, don't you?
- Yes...Yes.   - Will you send the manuscripts to that address?
- 你会将手搞寄来吗？
- 是，是的
- Of course.  - Please don't forget.
- 当然
- 请别忘记
我们一定慎重的去芜存菁
And rest assured We shall make a very careful selection of what is to survive.
再见
Goodbye.
苦艾酒，两杯
Absinthe. Two.
跟我说，你是否爱我
Tell me if you love me.
你知道我很喜欢你
You know I'm very fond of you.
你爱我吗？
Do you love me?
爱
Yes.
那就把手放在桌上
Then Put your hand on the table.
What?
什么？
把手放桌上
Put your hand on the table.
手心朝上
Palm upwards.
他死后，我夜夜见到他
Since he died, I see him every night...
我的伟大和荣耀的罪
my great and radiant sin.
我们一直很快乐……一直
We were always happy... always.
我都记得
I remember.
我找到了
I found it.
What?
什么？
永恒
Eternity.
就是太阳与海
It's the sun mingled...
交相辉映
with the sea.
剧终 谢谢观赏